I have written a small C program.
我写了一个 C 小程序。
It’s supposed to be a simple license check.
功能是一个简单的许可证检查。
So you can execute it and you can supply a key as argument and it will be checked.
所以你可以执行它，可以提供一个 密钥 作为参数，它会被检查。
Our goal is to crack this program so we don’t have to use a valid license key.
我们的目标是破解这个程序，这样我们就不会必须使用有效的许可证密钥。
I have made this program available through a github repository.
我已经把这个可工作的程序，放在 GitHub 存储库。
You can download it from github.com/liveoverflow/liveoverflow_youtube or you can install ‘git’ with ‘sudo
你可以从 github.com/liveoverflow/liveoverflow_youtube 或者先安装 git
apt-get install git’ and get the whole repository with ‘git clone’ and the address you can
"sudo apt get install git"，并使用"git clone"获取整个存储库，
see on github.
获取地址就在 Github。
We will probably talk more about what git is later.
我们也许会稍后谈谈 Git 是啥，。
For now it’s enough to know, that this is a way how developers can program together
现在，只要知道，这个开发人员能够一起编程(同一程序)的
on a project.
合作方法
And I use it to share some stuff.
和我会用它，来分享一些东西。
To have a look at the binary assembler code, we can use a program called gdb.
要了解二进制汇编代码，我们会使用到一个叫做 gdb 的程序。
The GNU Debugger.
GNU调试程序。
So type ‘gdb’ and the path to the binary.
所以，只要键入"gdb"和二进制文件的路径。
So every C program has a main function, remember?
还记得，每个C程序都有一个 main 函数吗？
So let’s type in ‘disassemble main’ which will display all assembler instructions
那么让我们输入"disassemble main"，它将显示在 main 函数中的
from the main function.
所有汇编指令。
But urgh, do you see how ugly that looks?
但是，呃，你也看到它有多难看啦？
That’s the horrible at&amp;t syntax.
这是非常糟糕的 at&amp;t 语法。
So type in ‘set disassembly-flavor intel’.
所以，键入"set disassembly flavor intel"。
Remember that you can use tab completion here as well.
请记住，您可以在此处使 tab补全 噢。
Now ‘disassemble main’ again, and now it’s much more readable.
现在再次"disassemble main"，现在它的可读性更高。
Ok.
好啊。
So.
所以。
It looks complicated.
还是，看起来很复杂。
But you can ignore most of it.
但你可以忽略其中的大部分。
First of all get a high-level view of it.
首先，要对它有一个高层次的了解。
It doesn’t make sense to start going through this instruction by instruction.
一条接一条地查看指令，从初学者角度是不可取的。
This main function obviously calls other functions.
因为，这个 main 函数显然调用其他函数（绕晕你）。
So just draw a mental picture of the rough control flow.
所以，只要画一张粗略的控制流程。
I will actually print out this assembler code and use a pen.
我将用钢笔，实际打印出这个汇编代码。
That’s how I did it in the beginning and still do it when I encounter more complex
当我遇到更复杂的代码时，这正是我一开始会做的。
And remember to just ignore most of the stuff, concentrate on the actual flow.
记住要忽略大部分的事情，注意实际流向。
So at the start it arrives at a compare with the number 2.
所以在开始的时候，与数字 2 做了个比较。
And afterwards a ‘jump not equal’.
然后是"jump not equal"。
So something is checked if it is 2.
所以，如果是 2，就要检查。
If that is the case, we proceed to a ‘printf’.
如果是这种情况，我们将继续进行"printf"。
Which we know is a function to display text.
我们知道，它是一个显示文本的函数。
Then comes a ‘strcmp’, if you don’t know that function, read the man page of it.
之后有个"strcmp"，如果你不了解这个函数，阅读它的手册页。
‘man 3 strcmp’ - so this compares two strings and returns 0 if both strings were
"man 3 strcmp" - 所以，这函数是比较了两个字符串，如果相等就返回 0
After that call we see another ‘jump not equal’ so if the zero flag is not set, there
调用后，我们看到另一个"jump not equal"，所以，如果没有设置零标志，
will be a ‘puts’ call.
这里会是一个"puts" call。
Use the man page to figure out what it does, but it just prints text like printf.
使用手册页了解它的作用，但它只是像 printf 一样打印文本。
So if the original compare with the number 2 was not true, then it would jump to this
所以如果原始数据与数字 2 比较，结果不是真的，那么它会跳到
address 0x400623, which is at offset main+102.
地址 0x400623 ，偏移 main+102 。
So in that case it prints some other text with ‘puts’ and exits.
所以，在这种情况下，它会"puts"，打印其他文本和退出程序。
I always add the addresses, or at least part of the address, from important locations,
我总是添加重要的地址，或者至少部分地址的记录，
so I know where I am.
所以，我能知道运行到了哪里。
This will help you later when we step through the program.
这对你以后，一步一步走程序过程，有所帮助。
Now we have one branch missing.
现在，我们缺了一个分支(branch)。
If this compare was incorrect, this branch would jump to offset main+90.
如果这个比较不正确，这个分支会跳到，偏移 main+90。
Which also just prints text.
也只是打印文本。
Some jumps are still missing, but you can add them to get a nice control-flow graph.
仍缺了一些 jump ，但你可以添加它们，以得到一个很好的控制流程图。
Now let’s actually execute this and step through it.
现在，让我们实际执行和一步步前进。
You can then draw which path through the graph you have taken on your paper.
然后你可以在你纸上画出，你有流程图的哪条路。
To do do this we first set a breakpoint at the start of main with ‘break *main’.
为此，首先使用"break *main"，在 main 函数开头设个断点。
Breakpoint is set, now use ‘run’ to start the program.
设置好了断点，现在使用"run"启动程序。
Starting program and we hit the breakpoint 1 at this address.
启动程序，我们到达了这个断点1的地址。
A breakpoint is a point where execution stops.
断点是执行停滞的点。
Now look at the registers with ‘info registers’.
现在，用"info registers"看到寄存器。
Here you can see that RIP, the instruction pointer, points to the first address in main.
在这里你可以看到那个RIP，指令指针，指向 main 中的第一个地址。
Now use ‘si’ to step one instruction.
现在使用"si"，执行一条指令。
Now we are at a new address in main.
现在，我们在 main 中的一个新地址。
‘info registers’ and you see the changed instruction pointer.
"info registers"和，您看到指令指针的更改。
So now just step through it all and follow the addresses in your control graph.
所以现在，只要一步一步调试，跟着控制图中的地址。
But use ‘ni’ instead of ‘si’, because ‘si’ would step into function calls.
但是使用"ni"，而不是"si"，因为"si"会进到函数的调用。
But we only want to step through this main function and not follow stuff like ‘puts’.
但我们只想跨过这条 main 函数，而不是细看像"puts"这样的东西。
Ok did you notice when we jumped?
好吧，我们跳的时候你注意到了吗？
The jump was at 5d0, and then the next instruction was at 623.
跳到 5d0，然后是下一条指令，是 623。
So we followed the jump, which means whatever was compared to 2, was not 2.
所以我们跟着跳，这里意味着，与 2 相比，不为真。
And then the program printed the Usage information after 628, which was the last ‘puts’ call.
然后程序在 628 之后，打印用法信息，这是最后一个"puts"调用。
So we can write down, that this ‘puts’ prints the ‘Usage’ information.
所以我们可以写下，这个"puts"打印用法信息。
Now it’s pretty clear, that we didn’t pass a key to this program.
现在很明显，我们并没有将密钥传递给此程序（才导致这分支的执行)。
Which means the check was looking at the arguments if we supplied a license key.
这意味着，检查是在有参数，我们提供了许可证密钥的情况下，才执行。
So let’s run the program again, but this time with a random license key.
让我们再次运行程序，但是这一次使用随机许可证密钥。
Yes we want to start the program again.
好的，我们重新启动程序。
Now do the same.
现在，做同样的事情。
‘ni’, ‘ni’.
"ni"，"ni"。
Now we are at 5d0 again, will we jump this time?
现在我们又到 5d0 了，这次我们会跳同个点吗？
No! cool!
没有！酷！
So the next branch we expect is at 609.
所以，我们预计下一个分支是 609。
Let’s ‘ni’ and see what happens.
再"ni"，看看会发生什么。
AH!
啊！
Another print text.
另一个打印文本。
So that ‘printf’ is the info that a license key will be checked.
所以，这个"printf"，表示这个许可证密钥，将被检查。
‘ni’.
"ni"。
Now comes the branch.
现在，分支来了。
Ok we arrived at 609, let’s see where we are afterwards.
好的，我们到了609，让我们看看，我们后来在哪里。
At 617.
617。
So we did jump, which means that the strcmp failed.
所以，我们确实跳了，但也意味着，strcmp 失败了。
And when we continue with ‘ni’ we see that it’s wrong.
当我们继续"ni"时，我们看到这是错误的。
Ok.
好吧。
Let’s set a breakpoint just before the last compare and run the program again.
让我们在最后一个比较之前，设置一个断点，并再次运行程序。
Remember that you can easily copy&amp;paste values in the terminal by simply marking something
请记住，您在终端上简单地做标记，可以轻松地复制和粘贴值，
and pressing your mousewheel.
然后，按你的鼠标滚轮。
Now ‘run’ again.
现在再"run"一次。
Breakpoint 1.
断点 1。
Now ‘continue’.
现在，"continue"。
This will run the program normally again, until we hit the next breakpoint.
再次正常运行程序，直到我们到达下一个断点。
Now stopped before we execute the ‘test eax, eax’.
现在，在我们执行"test eax, eax"之前，歇歇
EAX just refers to the first 32bit of the 64bit RAX register.
eax 只是指向 64位 rax寄存器的前32位。
So it’s value is hex 0xE.
所以它的值是，十六进制 0xE。
Let’s set this to 0, which would indicate that the ‘strcmp’ was correct and returned
让我们把它设为 0，这表示"strcmp"是正确的，并返回
a 0. ‘set $eax=0’.
一个 0。'set $eax=0'。
‘info registers’ and you can see that it’s now 0.
(接着)"info registers"，你可以看到现在是 0。
Now use ‘ni’ again to step and follow your control path.
现在再次使用"ni"步进，并跟随你的控制流程路径。
‘Access Granted!’
'Access Granted!'(已授予访问权限！)
YAY!
呀呀呀！
We circumvented the license check!
我们避开了许可证检查！
It think that’s pretty cool!
我觉得，很酷！
And you can always write your own little C program trying to make it more secure, and
你可以一直写你自己的小C程序，尝试让它更安全，以及
then crack it yourself again.
之后你自己再破解一次。
You will notice that it’s impossible to make a program uncrackable.
你会发现，想让程序无法破解，常规操作是不可能做到的。
Those kind of challenges are called ‘crackme’.
这种挑战被称为"crackme"。
People create small programs that have to be cracked.
（那里）人们创造不得不破解的小程序。
Or more often you have to create a valid keygen.
或者更频繁地创建，有效的 keygen。
If you think something like this is fun, checkout http://crackmes.de/.
如果你认为这样的事情很有趣，查看 http://crackmes.de/。
Creating control graphs like we just did is pretty useful.
像我们刚才那样画出控制流程图，是非常有用。
That’s why there are some programs that do that for us.
这就是为什么，会有些程序帮我们做这件事。
Here are three different examples of this specific control graph.
这里有，三个关于特定控制图的不同例子。
First is HopperApp, second is IDAPro and the last one is from radare2.
第一个是 hopperapp，第二个是 IDAPro，和最后一个来自 radare2。
See you hopefully next time when we use some different tools to explore this licence check
希望下次，我们用不同工具，能更多地探索
binary a bit more.
这个二进制程序。
Let’s figure out together the basic concepts of a CPU.
让我们把CPU的基本概念，总结总结
Computers have different memory to store stuff - so first we need something to store the
计算机有存储东西的不同内存 - 所以首先我们需要一些东西来储存
machine code in.
机器代码。
Let’s take a spreadsheet and imagine that this is memory.
让我们拿个电子表格，把它想成为内存。
You can store values in it and each memory cell has an address, which is the number on the left.
您可以在它里面存储变量，和每个内存单元格都有一个地址，该地址值在左边。
And I will use the 2nd column to write some comments in there.
我会用第二栏，写一些注释。
As you can see there are some hexadecimal numbers stored in this memory.
正如，你所看到的，有一些十六进制数字，存储在此内存中。
And at first it looks very random, but that is our machine code and soon you will understand
起初看起来很随机，但是，这就是我们的机器代码，很快你就会明白。
So the first thing the CPU needs to have is something to keep track where in memory the
所以CPU需要有的第一件东东，就是保持 CPU 当前跟踪在内存的位置。
Which means we shoud add a little storage for our CPU and call it the “Instruction
这意味着，要给我们的CPU，应该增加一点储藏区，称之为"指令指针"。
This little storage area will contain the address of memory the CPU is looking at the
这个小储藏区，将包含CPU当前时刻，查看的内存地址
So obviously our program starts from the top, so the address will be 1.
所以，很明显我们的程序是，从顶层开始的，所以地址是 1。
Now let’s start the CPU, it looks at address 1 and reads 48, AA, 14.
现在，让我们启动CPU，它查看地址1，读到了 48, aa, 14。
But what do those numbers mean?
但是，这些数字是什么意思？
The CPU knows that 48 means it has to MOVE data around.
CPU知道 48 意味着，它必须 move 周围的数据。
The AA means the destination of that move. and the 14 is the source.
aa 表示移动的目的地。14 是源。
So in address 14 we can see the number 42.
所以在地址14，我们可以看到数字42。
And the destination is another small storage unit inside the CPU.
目的地是，CPU内部的另一个小仓库单元。
So the CPU will move the 42 into it’s small storage area called AA.
所以，CPU会把 42，move 到它的称为aa的小储存区。
So this instruction is done, and the CPU increases the Instruction pointer by one.
这个指令完成了，CPU 让指令指针 增加 1 。
And we start over.
然后，重新开始。
The CPU reads the current value at the address of it’s instruction pointer.
CPU读取它的指令指针，所指向地址的当前值。
So it reads 48 again which means move, and this time it’s moving the content of address
所以，它再次读取48，这意味着 move ，和这次移动的地址是
15 into the small storage BB.
15，其中的内容会移动到小储存区 bb。
Notice how I use brackets around the 15.
注意，我是在15左右，使用了括号。
This indicates that 15 is an address, and we actually reference the content of 15, which
这表示15是一个地址，并且我们实际上，引用了 15(这个地址) 的内容，
is 66.
是数字66。
And not the number 15 itself.
而不是，数字15本身。
Instruction done, increase the Instruction pointer.
指令完成，指令指针增加1。
The next address contains 83, AA and BB.
下一个地址，包含 83、aa 和 bb。
The CPU knows that 83 means COMPARE.
CPU知道83，表示比较(COMPARE)。
And it compares the values in AA and BB.
它比较了 aa和bb(地址) 中的值。
Now it has to somehow remember the result of this compare.
现在，它必须以某种方式，记住这一比较结果。
So let’s add another small storage that stores this result.
所以，我们再加一个小的存储空间，存储此结果。
We call it Zero Flag.
我们称之为零标志(Zero Flag)。
You know what an intelligent way is to compare two numbers?
你知道'比较'两个数字的聪明方法是什么吗？
If you subtract them from each other and their result is 0, they were the same.
如果，你从对方身上减去他们，而结果是0，说明它们是相同的。
If the result is not zero, they were different.
如果，结果不是零，它们就是不同的。
So this is what the CPU does.
这就是 CPU所做的。
66-42 is 24, so that’s not 0.
66-42 是24，所以不是 0。
So we set the zero flag to false.
所以我们把零标志，设为 false (假的)。
Instruction done, next one is at address 4.
指令完成，下一个在地址 4。
The CPU reads a 75 and 07.
CPU读取 75和07。
75 Stands for JUMP If not equal.
75，代表如果不相等，就 jump 。
And 07 is the address where to jump to.
07 是跳到的地址。
So the CPU checks the state of the Zero Flag.
所以CPU，检查零标志的状态。
And The Zero flag is set to FALSE, so the previous compare was not equal.
零标志设为假，所以上一个比较，不相等。
Which means it jumps to the destination 07.
这意味着它，会跳到目的地 07。
A jump is easy.
简单的 jump 操作
The CPU just sets its Instruction Pointer to 07.
CPU只是设置，其指令指针，指向07。
Ok so the next instruction is at address 7.
好的，下一条指令在地址 7。
And it reads E8 and 17.
它的读数是 e8和17。
E8 In this case stands for print a text.
在这种情况下，e8 代表打印文本。
And the text can be found at address 17.
文本可以，在 地址17 找到。
But 17 doesn’t contain text?
但 (地址)17 不包含文本？
Well, for a computer everything is numbers.
对计算机来说，一切都是数字。
Like those instructions the CPU executes, they are just numbers.
就像CPU执行的那些指令一样，它们只是数字。
So text is made out of numbers too.
所以文本，也是由数字组成的。
Remember how I brushed over ASCII values in a previous video?
记得，我以前的视频，是怎样转换 ASCII 值的吗？
Now it’s the time to pull up the ascii man page again.
现在是时候，再拿出 ASCII man 大全。
So type ‘man ascii’ In the terminal.
所以在终端中，输入'man ascii'。
Now try to find hex 4E and 4F.
现在试着找到(Hex) 4e 和4f 。
Haa.. ok.
哈..。ok。
So they stand for ‘N’ and ‘O’.
所以它们，代表"N"和"O"。
Which means the computer will print ‘NO’.
这意味着计算机，将打印"NO"。
So looks like this code simply compares two numbers.
所以看起来，这段代码只是比较了两个数字。
I will not go over the case when those two numbers are the same, but you should try it
这里我不会去看两个数字相等的情况，但你应该自己试试看
That’s crazy, huh?
太疯狂了，对吧？
CPU simply reads the memory sequentially and does whatever it reads.
CPU只是按顺序读取内存，和做它读到的任何事。
And programmers can build crazy complex stuff with that.
程序员以此，可以制造出疯狂复杂的东西。
Now let me change the text a little bit so it reflects more the reality of how we write
现在让我把文字改一下，让它更好地反映，我们是如何编写汇编的现实。
Basically just abbreviation of it.
基本上只是，它的缩写。
Also don’t get confused with the order of parameters.
也不要混淆参数的顺序。
simply think of it like a variable assignment in programming.
简单地把它，想象成在编程中，一个变量赋值。
This was a very simple example, but the real world is not much different.
这是一个非常简单的例子，但是在现实的世界，并没有多大不同。
People just came up with a lot more instructions that might be interesting and wrote complex
(现实)人们只是更多的指令，这可能会很有趣，毕竟可以编写解决复杂难题的代码。
But at their core they are simple like that.
但它们的核心，是清晰的，与前面的例子一样简单。